Guide to the Wesley Works archive, 1676-1996 and undated, bulk 1724-1791, 1960-1996 RL.01368
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- The Methodist Societies Series (Volumes 9-10), 1739-1799, 1864-1869, 1958-1991 and undated, 12 boxes
  - Minutes of the Conference Subseries (Volume 10), 1739-1799, 1864-1869, 1958-1991 and undated
    - Other research materials, 1739-1799, 1975-1980 and undated
      Various uncategorized research files and notes consisting of some or all of the categories above (correspondence, photocopies, preliminary texts, and typescripts). Many though not all of these files comprise research on the names and stationing of British and American preachers, concluding with the extensive list at the end of this folder group, "Wesley's Preachers," which was apparently rejected as being too long to include in the published volume. Arranged alphabetically.
      - American Preachers, 1773-1799, 1980 (Box 53)
      - British Preachers' Stationing, 1744-1764--Summary, 1980 (Box 53)
      - Corrections to the Conference Journal, 1784-1791 (Box 53)
      - Notes, photocopies, and teaching materials on status, stationing, and other topics, 1784, 1975 and undated (Box 53)
      - Notes and references, 1739-1979 and undated (Box 53)
      - Wesley's preachers, undated, Folders 1-2 of 4 (Box 53)
        Alphabetical index, circa 250 pages, of more than 600 18th-century preachers. Each entry lists preacher's stations in chronological order, followed by citations for the sources of this information. Undated but probably prepared in the late 1970s or 1980s, by Baker and his daughter Enid Hickingbotham.
      - Wesley's preachers, undated, Folders 3-4 of 4 (Box 54)
- The Appeals to Men of Reason and Religion and Certain Related Open Letters Series (Volume 11), 1742-1791, 1968-1983 and undated, 4 boxes
  The series holds materials for the first-published volume of the Bicentennial Edition, The Appeals to Men of Reason and Religion and Certain Related Open Letters (Vol. 11). The Appeals volume gathers printed materials and open letters by Wesley in which he attempted to publicly clarify his ecclesiastical and theological positions, sometimes out of the need to respond to attacks and correct public misconceptions of the Methodist societies.
  Volume 11 was the first volume published by Oxford University Press, in 1975; it was also re-published by Abingdon Press in 1987. Materials here relate only to the initial edition. The series opens with a short folder group of correspondence, followed by a single folder of various photographs used in the volume. The remainder of the series consists of successive drafts of typescripts and various stages of proofs. Typescripts include both preliminary texts, with notes on stemmata, and styled texts. Most of the correspondence and discussion here is between Baker and Gerald R. Cragg, unit editor for the Appeals.
  - Correspondence and Illustrations
    - Correspondence, 1968-1974, 2 folders (Box 55)
    - Photography of engravings of and letters by Wesley, and title pages, 1742-1791, 1974-1983 (Box 55)
  - Typescripts--preliminary texts and stemmata
    - An Earnest Appeal to Men of Reason and Religion (1743), undated (Box 55)
    - A Further Appeal to Men of Reason and Religion (1745)--texts and comparison of editions, undated, 4 folders (Box 55)
    - A Letter to the Right Reverend Lord Bishop of London (1747), 1971 and undated (Box 55)
    - A Letter to the Author of "The Enthusiasm of Methodists and Papists Compared" (1750), undated (Box 55)
    - A Second Letter to the Author of "The Enthusiasm ..." (1751), undated (Box 56)
    - A Second Letter to the Lord Bishop of Exeter (1752), undated (Box 56)
    - A Letter to the Rev. Mr. Horne (1762), undated (Box 56)
    - A Letter to the Right Reverend the Lord Bishop of Gloucester (1763), undated (Box 56)
  - Typescripts--styled texts
    - A Further Appeal to Men of Reason and Religion (1745)--texts and comparison of editions, undated, 3 folders (Box 56)
    - A Letter to the Author of "The Enthusiasm of Methodists and Papists Compared" (1750), undated (Box 56)
    - A Second Letter to the Author of "The Enthusiasm ..." (1751), undated (Box 56)
    - A Second Letter to the Lord Bishop of Exeter (1752), undated (Box 56)
    - A Letter to the Right Reverend the Lord Bishop of Gloucester (1763), undated (Box 56)
  - Other typescripts, proofs, and index
    - Typescripts--carbon copies for press, 1972, Folders 1-2 of 12 (Box 56)
    - Typescripts--carbon copies for press, 1972, Folders 3-12 of 12 (Box 57)
    - Typescript and extra copies of appendix, undated (Box 57)
    - Indexes, for press, undated (Box 57)
    - Proofs, 1974, Folders 1-2 of 4 (Box 57)
    - Proofs, 1974, Folders 3-4 of 4 (Box 58)
    - Proofs, top copy, 1974, 7 folders (Box 58)
      A note of Frank Baker states that this typescript contains corrections too late for publishing.
    - Proofs--appendix, undated (Box 58)
    - Bound proof, 1974 (Box 58)
- Doctrinal and Controversial Treatises Series (Volumes 12-13), 1976-1994 and undated, 1 box
  Correspondence, notes, and a typescript for Volumes 12 and 13, in preparation. Although not extensive, the correspondence contains discussion between Baker and a succession of unit editors over the course of some twenty years, including original unit editors John Deschner (Vol. 12) and William R. Cannon (Vol. 13). A long typescript of almost 800 pages was prepared by Baker in 1981 for a subsequent unit editor, Robert Cushman (Vol. 12). Although this typescript is a fair copy, most of its sections contain notes on stemma and extensive bracketed notes by Baker on all aspects of the text. The series concludes with a prospective list of titles, prepared around 1980, for The Defence of Christianity (the original title for Vol. 13). In addition to the materials included here, shorter typescripts for individual works may be found in Arminian Magazine. in the Catechetical/Educational Works Series (Vol. 15). Unit editors included Paul Chilcote and Randy Maddox (Vol. 12); and Ken Collins (Vol. 13).
  - Correspondence, 1976-1994 (Box 59)
  - Typescript, circa 1981, 7 folders (Box 59)
  - An Attempt to Unite the British Methodists--text for Vol. 9 or Vol. 12, (1749), 1979 (Box 59)
  - List for The Defence of Christianity (Vol. 13), 1971, 1980 and undated (Box 59)
- Social/Political Tracts Series (Volume 14), 1969-1980, and Catechetical/Educational Works Series (Volume 15), 1740-1791, 1969-1980, 1992 and undated, 3 boxes
  Volumes 14 and 15 were originally conceived as a single unit to be entitled "Pastoral and Educational Works" and edited by A. Lamar Cooper. This plan lasted until at least the mid-1980s, encompassing all the materials gathered here. Since current rather than original titles are being used for the series in this inventory, the assignment of these typescripts to Volume 15 is somewhat arbitrary--in reality, there is no differentiation between the two volumes here. There are preliminary texts for each tract as originally planned for the volume; copies of a collated typescript; and correspondence. Unit editors were David Hempton (Vol. 14) and Rex Matthews and Rebekah Miles (Vol. 15).
  - Summary, correspondence, notes, 1969-1980 (Box 60)
  - Preliminary and styled texts, A-T and undated, Folders 1-28 of 40 (Box 60)
    Typescripts of forty Wesley titles published from the 1740s-1790s. Baker's edits probably date to the 1970s or early 1980s. Arranged alphabetically by title, with this box containing "The Advantage of the Members of the Church" through "Serious Thoughts Upon the Perseverence of the Saints."
  - Preliminary and styled texts, A-T and undated, Folders 29-40 of 40 (Box 61)
    "A Short Account of the School at Kingswood" through "Thoughts Upon Slavery."
  - Typescript, undated, 5 folders (Box 61)
    Full typescript, circa 500 pp. plus notes, including texts for An Extract of the Christian's Pattern, A Short Account of the Life and Death of the Rev. John Fletcher, and numerous shorter works.
  - Typescripts--edited, undated (Box 61)
    Further edits on Extract and other portions of the fair copy above.
  - Arminian Magazine, 1778-1791, 1992 and undated, 5 folders (Box 62)
    Contains unedited typescripts extracted from Wesley's magazine; organized by year, not volume, with brief notes and queries about individual works' selection for Volumes 12, 13, 14, 15, or 16. Folder 1 contains an extensive contents list for the magazine from 1779-1791.
- Editorial Works Series (Volume 16), 1920-1984, 1 box
  This volume focuses on JW's extensive work in editing and re-publishing the works of other authors. Materials for this series comprise only a few folders, ending a few months after the 1983 death of the original unit editor, T. Walter Herbert. Correspondence between Baker and Herbert begins in 1970 and continues through the early 1980s. One correspondence folder contains the main piece of original research and writing found here, a 1982 draft of Herbert's introduction for the volume. The remainder of the series consists of photocopied articles on the history of printing and principles of bibliography; their direct relationship to this volume is unclear, and they are similar to other materials to be found in the Bibliography Series. Unit editor Randy Maddox replaced Herbert.
  - Early correspondence with T. Walter Herbert, 1969-1976 (Box 62)
  - Later correspondence with Herbert, including his introduction for Volume 16, 1980-1984 (Box 62)
  - Research--articles on the history of printing and bibliography, 1920-1970, 2 folders (Box 62)
- Medical Writings Series (Volume 17), 1745-1791, 1973-1996 and undated, 1 boxes
  This volume focuses on Wesley's writings on medicine and other topics in the sciences. In addition to a few folders of texts--mainly photocopies--at the end of the series, the materials here comprise two small groups of correspondence and research, one from the 1970s and one from 1990s. The former is concerned with general planning for this unit, which early on had the broader title, or rather theme, of "Medicine and Natural Philosophy." The later group of correspondence is mainly between Baker and James Donat, who first contacted Baker in 1995 about research he was conducting on Wesley's Primitive Physick, independently of the Wesley Works Editorial Project. Donat served as co-editor of this unit along with Randy Maddox.
  - Correspondence and research on Wesley's natural philosophy and Survey of the Wisdom of God in the Creation, 1791, 1973-1974, 1991 and undated, 2 folders (Box 63)
  - Correspondence with James Donat on texts of various works, 1775-1776, 1985, 1995-1996 and undated, 2 folders (Box 63)
  - Collection of Receipts for the Use of the Poor (includes preliminary typescript), 1745-1746 and undated (Box 63)
  - The Desideratum; or, Electricity Made Plain and Useful--photocopies, 1771-1778 (Box 63)
  - An Extract From Dr. Cadogan's Dissertation on the Gout--typescript transcribed and edited by Donat, 1996 (Box 63)
  - Primitive Physick--notes, photocopies, stemma, and unpublished article by FB, 1755-1785, 1979-1989 and undated (Box 63)
  - Thoughts on the Sin of Onan, 1779 and undated (Box 63)
- Journals and Diaries Series (Volumes 18-24), 1735-1790, 1968-1996 and undated, 16 boxes
  The series Journals and Diaries is among the largest in the collection, covers one of the two largest units in the Bicentennial Edition, and is also co-edited by Richard P. Heitzenrater, who succeeded Baker as General Editor for the WWEP. Heitzenrater is also the editor of a later, closely-related series, the Oxford Diaries (Volume 32). There is no material in the collection related to this volume-in-preparation, but materials housed elsewhere may pertain to it.
  Contains correspondence between the unit editors and Frank Baker; research on the Georgia Journal and a preliminary text by Richard Heitzenrater; drafts of Vol. 18 introduction; a significant number of notes by Frank Baker relating to the editing and publication of the volumes including "Safeguarding Wesley's Style," in which the decisions in preserving 18th-century vernacular are explained; and an incomplete collection of galleys and page proofs of Vol. 18-24. Unit editors for Volumes 18-24 were W. Reginald Ward (Journals) and Richard P. Heitzenrater (Diaries).
  - General Planning Subseries, 1735-1790, 1968-1996 and undated (Box 63)
    - Correspondence, chronological, 1968-1991 and undated, 2 folders (Box 64)
      Contains drafts and notes for FB's article The Birth of John Wesley's Journal, 1970.
    - Correspondence--Heitzenrater, 1969-1986 and undated (Box 64)
      Contains letter from Heitzenrater to Baker, 1969 July 31, in which he describes his discovery that day of the Benjamin Ingham diary, which held a key to the cipher Wesley used in his Oxford diaries.
    - Miscellaneous notes and photocopies, 1749-1759, 1987 and undated (Box 64)
    - Chart of Volumes 18-24, undated (Box 64)
    - Proofs and final editing, 1974-1994 (Box 64)
    - Safeguarding Wesley's style, 1989 and undated, 2 folders (Box 64)
    - Baker's personal preface to Appendix A:1 ("Wesley's Text"), 1993 (Box 64)
    - Baker's note on variants 1770-1774, 1996 (Box 64)
    - Journal 2 final printing, undated (Box 64)
    - Journal leaves, J.W. III.12, 1756-1758 (Box 64)
    - Miscellaneous extracts of manuscripts, 1735-1775, 1985-1990 (Box 64)
    - Miscellaneous notes--stemmata, undated (Box 64)
    - Preliminary extracts, 1974-1991 and undated, Folders 1-4 of 5 (Box 64)
      Note: Original trial batch for Oct. 1743-June 1744, followed by preliminary extracts for Journal volumes 13-15, 1762-1770; and volume 19, 1779-1782.
    - Preliminary extracts, 1974-1991 and undated, Folder 5 of 5 (Box 65)
    - Styled extracts, Journals 1-8 (1736-1751), 1986 and undated, Folders 1-8 of 24 (Box 65)
      Typescripts edited for style, together with stemmata notes for some volumes.
    - Styled extracts, Journals 9-15 (1751-1770), undated, Folders 9-17 of 24 (Box 66)
      Journal 13 (1762-1765) contains an additional folders of footnotes by FB apparently not used in the published version.
    - Styled extracts, Journals 16-21 (1770-1790), 1983, 1996 and undated, Folders 18-24 of 24 (Box 67)
    - First edited extracts, Journals 7-8 (1746-1751), undated, Folders 1-3 of 12 (Box 67)
      Fair copy typescripts that incorporate the extensive hand-edits from styled extracts above. This partial sequence picks up with Journal 7 and concludes with Journal 14.
    - First edited extracts, Journals 8-14 (1751-1768), undated, Folders 4-12 of 12 (Box 68)
    - First edited extracts--notes for Journals 14-16, undated, 3 folders (Box 68)
  - Volumes Subseries, 1735-1788, 1981-1996 and undated
    Correspondence, notes, typescripts, and proofs for individual volumes of the Journals and Diaries unit.
    - Journals and Diaries I (1725-1738) (Volume 18)
      - General files, 1981-1988 and undated
        - Correspondence, notes, 1981-1988, 3 folders (Box 68)
        - Introduction--correspondence, first draft, and later draft, 1986 and undated, 3 folders (Box 70)
      - Georgia diaries and journals (Box 69)
        - Wesley: Journal of Voyage to Georgia (1735-1738), and notes, undated (Box 69)
        - Georgia manuscript journals (1736-1738)--arranged photocopies (Reginald Ward), 1986 and undated, 6 folders (Box 69)
        - Preliminary texts--Heitzenrater typescript, 1986 (Box 69)
        - Preliminary texts, appendix--Baker typescript, undated, 2 folders (Box 70)
        - Manuscript journals and diaries (typescript, combined--May 1-Nov. 1, 1736), undated (Box 70)
      - Journal Extracts (1735-1738)--various typescripts, 1986 and undated (Box 70)
        - Journal I--Appendix MS JRN and DIA 1, 1735-1736 (Box 70)
        - Journal I Duplicate, 1735-1736 (Box 70)
        - Journal I unedited typescript, 1735-1738, 2 folders (Box 70)
        - Heitzenrater typescript: Georgia and London diaries, 1735-1738, and undated, Folder 1 of 2 (Box 70)
        - Heitzenrater typescript: Georgia and London diaries, 1735-1738, and undated, Folder 2 of 2 (Box 71)
        - Typescript top copy, with footnotes, 1986, 4 folders (Box 71)
        - Carbon copy of revised text, 1736-1738 and undated, 4 folders (Box 71)
        - Revisions, 1986 (Box 71)
        - Extract I footnotes by Heitzenrater, 1986 (Box 71)
      - Proofs and Galleys, 1987-1988
        - Page proofs, redated, 1987 (Box 71)
        - Galleys, 1987-1988, Folders 1-2 of 5 (Box 71)
        - Galleys, 1987-1988, Folders 3-5 of 5 (Box 79)
    - Journals and Diaries II (1738-1743) (Volume 19)
      - Correspondence, 1987 (Box 72)
      - Extracts 3-5, working copy (1738-1743), undated, 4 folders (Box 72)
      - Extracts 3-5, working notes by Baker, undated (Box 72)
      - Corrected page proofs, Volume 19, 1989, Folders 1-3 of 4 (Box 72)
      - Corrected page proofs, Volume 19, 1989, Folder 4 of 4 (Box 73)
      - Galleys, Extracts 3-5, 1989, 3 folders (Box 79)
    - Journals and Diaries III (1743-1754) (Volume 20)
      - Extract 6 (1743-1746), working copy and Baker's original notes pages, undated, 3 folders (Box 73)
      - Extract 7 (1746-1749), working copy, undated, 2 folders (Box 73)
      - Extract 8 (1749-1751), working copy, undated, 2 folders (Box 73)
      - Extracts 7 and 8, Baker's original notes pages, undated (Box 73)
      - Extract 9 (1751-1754), working copy, undated, 2 folders (Box 74)
      - Heitzenrater final transcript, 1990, 6 folders (Box 74)
      - Corrected page proofs, 1990, 4 folders (Box 74)
      - Galleys, Extracts 6-9, 1990, 4 folders (Box 75)
    - Journals and Diaries IV (1755-1765) (Volume 21), 1758-1762, and undated
      - Extract 11 (1758-1760), working copy, undated (Box 75)
      - Extract 12 (1760-1762), working copy, undated, 2 folders (Box 75)
      - Extracts 10-12 (1755-1762), new working copy, undated, Folders 1-4 of 8 (Box 75)
      - Extracts 10-12 (1755-1762), new working copy, undated, Folders 4-8 of 8 (Box 76)
      - Heitzenrater final transcript, circa 1991-1992, 4 folders (Box 76)
    - Journals and Diaries V (1765-1775) (Volume 22), 1770-1994, and undated (Box 77)
      - Proof correspondence, 1992 and undated (Box 77)
      - Extracts 15 (1768-1770), 16 (1770-1773), and 17 (1773-1776), working copy, undated, 5 folders (Box 77)
      - Page proofs with FB's unused edits, 1993, 4 folders (Box 78)
        An extended note by Baker on these folders explains that this copy of the page proofs contains hundreds of his suggestions, not used by Heitzenrater in the published version, to retain Wesley's original punctuation and spelling. Baker further explains that both he and Heitzenrater as General Editor had good reasons for disagreeing and asks that this alternate copy of the proofs be retained.
    - Journals and Diaries VI (1776-1786) (Volume 23), 1994
      - Correspondence, 1991-1992 (Box 78)
      - Extract 18 (1776-1779) typescript, 1991, 2 folders (Box 78)
      - Extract 20 proof mistakes, 1994 (Box 78)
      - Entry in bibliography, undated (Box 78)
      - Miscellaneous notes to Vol. 20, undated (Box 78)
      - Notes, printouts, miscellaneous, 1991-1996 (Box 78)
    - Journals and Diaries VII (1787-1791) (Volume 24), 1782-1788
      - Photocopies of JW's journal, 1782-1788 (Box 79)
- Letters Series (Volumes 25-31), 1721-1996 and undated, 15 boxes
  The seven volumes of John Wesley's letters comprised one of the two units of the Bicentennial Edition for which Frank Baker was originally slated to be unit editor. Although he completed only the first two of those volumes--Letters I: 1721-1739 and Letters II: 1740-1755 (Volumes 25 and 26, respectively)--the Letters Series contains not only those materials but many more that Baker gathered in preparation for the entire series. The series is arranged in two large subseries, General Files and Volumes. The latter is composed mainly of materials specific to the two volumes published during Baker's lifetime, including correspondence, notes, and many versions of typescripts and proofs. The General Files Subseries, however, contains materials for Baker's preparation for all seven volumes, some of which extend well past the 1755 end-date of Volume 26. Among the highlights here are the hundreds of photocopies of manuscript letters, both to and from Wesley, collected from archives around the world. Although these are in theory available from the original holding archive, where known, the fact of their being collected in single place makes this a valuable resource for studying Wesley's correspondence and correspondents. Another item of interest, entirely unique to this collection, is the notebook labeled "Early log of Wesley letters." Undated but probably from the mid-1970s to early 1980s, this notebook sheds light on Baker's research methods as well as providing a resource for studying Wesley's correspondence. It lists in chronological order, from 1725 to 1791, the date, place written, recipient, place received, prior publication if any, and present archival location of some 4000 John Wesley manuscript letters around the world. Its content extends well beyond the content presently available in either the published volumes of the Bicentennial Edition or in the previous standard for Wesley's letters, the Telford edition.
  The Letters series (Vol. 25-31) showcases the meticulous work of Frank Baker, editor of the series: here is his correspondence with international libraries to obtain extant Wesley letters; research concerning Wesley's correspondents; and many layers of editing the letters. The Wesley Works Archive contains relevant photocopies, not original manuscripts, of JW's letters. The bulk of the materials relate to the two volumes of letters published during Baker's lifetime--volumes 25 and 26 of the Bicentennial Edition--which cover Wesley's letters through 1755. However, there are also some materials for volume 27 and many materials that document Baker's extensive preparation for the entire 7 volume letters unit. These last-named materials, however, actually appear first in the following arrangement, under the heading of General Planning. Following that are the materials for individual volumes of the Letters. Frank Baker was the original unit editor and saw the first two of seven volumes into publication. The unit editors for the remaining volumes were Ted Campbell and Philip Meadows.
  - General Planning Subseries, 1724-1996 and undated
    The General Planning Subseries is arranged in several folder groups that outline Baker's extensive preparations for the entire Letters unit. The first group, Acquisition of Letters, contains his notes on antiquarian catalogs, indexes he compiled of 19th century Methodist periodicals, and back issues of Sotheby catalogs, dating to the early 20th century, in which Wesley letters were offered for sale. Correspondence is composed of two types of materials: his contact with other Wesleyan scholars; and the hundreds of inquiries he made to international archives in the mid-1970s about their holding of Wesley manuscripts (the letters shown here are mainly replies in the negative).
    Folders grouped under Identification comprise files about letters with either questionable dating or attribution, but also many details about the physical characteristics of letters that help in their proper identification, such as franks, seals, watermarks, and how to identify not only Wesley's handwriting but that of his various scribes and amanuenses.
    Indexes and Logs houses Baker's and other scholars' work on listing and categorizing Wesley's voluminous letters. In addition to the folders in this group, several other card files and indexes can be found in the Frank Baker Papers, Subject Files Series, Card Files Subseries, which houses over 30 indexes and 40,000 cards that Baker compiled for his own use as well as that of the Project.